Guide to the Frank Schonfeld Papers WAG.027
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Frank Schonfeld Papers
1909-1992
1940-1979
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Schonfeld, Frank
Schonfeld, David
WAG.027
44 Linear Feet in 43 record cartons and 2 manuscript boxes
Frank Schonfeld was born in 1916, and died in 2011. After some training as a rabbi, he studied in the Social Action program at the New School. After World War II service in the Merchant Marines, he joined Local 1011 of the Painters union in 1945. In 1961, Schonfeld ran for secretary-treasurer of Brotherhood of Painters District Council 9 (New York City). He lost and the winning Rarback administration sued him for libel. He then launched a public campaign to clean up corruption in the union. Blocked from running in 1964, in 1966 he ran for secretary-treasurer and won. He held office for two terms, during which time he carried out a number of reforms to combat union corruption. In 1972, he was found guilty by a union trial board on charges later determined to be unfounded. Schonfeld's campaign to end union corruption led to the eventual indictments of key leaders. This collection provides an inside view of a trade distinguished by highly volatile employment cycles, corrupt practices, and successive waves of different ethnic groups making up the workforce. It includes correspondence, flyers, election materials, legal documents, agreements, bulletins, photographs and clippings.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
These papers were created and collected by Frank Schonfeld while a member and officer of the Painters District Council 9 (New York City) and his home Local, 1011 (which was later merged and became part of Local Union 19). The earliest records, dating from 1909 to 1927, were given to him by older members of his union. Other records date from Schonfeld's membership in the union, beginning in 1945, his years as secretary-treasurer of the District Council, 1967-1973, and from his later life. The records described here were donated to the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives in 1984 by Mr. Schonfeld. The accesion numbers associated with this gift are 1984.001, 1984.011. A later donation was given in 1999. The accession numbers associated with these materials are NPA.1999.024 and NPA.2001.007.
An additional box of photographs and artifacts was donated by David Schonfeld, Frank's son, in 2007. The accession number associated with these materials is 2014.119. In 2014, David donated his father's unpublished manuscript; the accession number associated with this gift is 2014.154 and the materials have been added to the collection as Series XXI.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Biographical Note
Frank Schonfeld (1916-2011), a rabbi's son and grandson, was groomed to join the family profession. He attended Yeshiva College, where he received his Bachelor's degree in philosophy, psychology, and education. With World War II looming, Schonfeld concluded that he could not preach what he no longer believed. He turned to the labor movement because he considered it to be the most important contemporary force to counter fascism, racism, and war.
Schonfeld attended the Rochdale Institute and joined the cooperative movement, went into factory work, and took a one-year course at the New School with Roger Baldwin (founder of the American Civil Liberties Union), whose Social Action program provided Schonfeld with useful organizing tools and experience. Schonfeld joined the Merchant Marines in 1943. During the war, he married his lifelong companion, Jean, and the couple moved to the Amalgamated Clothing Workers' first housing cooperative in the Bronx in 1945. That same year, Schonfeld joined the Brotherhood of Painters, Decorators and Paperhangers of America (later the International Brotherhood of Painters and Allied Trades). His first official position in the union was as recording secretary of Local Union 1011, the Jewish local.
The membership of the Brotherhood of Painters in New York City generally reflected the various waves of immigrants coming into the country, the development of different political tendencies, and the tensions brought on by changes in the U.S. economy.
Racketeers were a major force in Painters District Council 9 (as they were in many other NYC building trades unions) until the membership, under the leadership of Louis Weinstock's Communist Party-oriented administration, attempted to break their hold in the 1930s. Weinstock's alliance (with its base in the Rank-and-File Clubs) had its own drawbacks, and some members felt that their interests were neglected in favor of the CP's all-out efforts in support of World War II, including the no-strike pledge.
In 1946, the Progressive Painters Club ran Martin Rarback as a new reform candidate for secretary-treasurer of the District, and he won the post in 1947. Rarback's promised militant program led to some progressive changes in the union, but he soon became a party to dubious practices that pre-dated his administration.
In part, it was the nature of the painting trades that provided easy opportunities for kickback schemes, bid-rigging, favoritism, conspiracy, and other forms of corruption. The jobs were isolated, largely unsupervised by the union, and highly seasonal; there was often a shortage of work. The union business agents, who wielded considerable power, were responsible for placing workers, surveying worksite conditions, and negotiating with contractors. Without significant reforms to the so-called "job trust" or to the District Council 9, the door was open to racketeering Martin Rarback was indicted in 1966 in a major New York City Housing Authority bid-rigging and bribery conspiracy.
After 1947, the Rank-and-File Club carried on its opposition fight, but the Cold War political climate and the conservative drift of the labor movement made for an uphill battle, and the group experienced several years of setbacks, including the expulsion of its key leaders from the union. In spite of undercurrents of discontent, there were no contested district-wide elections from 1953 to 1961, and the Rank-and-File Club was barely able to maintain its presence in a few locals.
By 1961, Rarback's blatant favoritism had created such dissatisfaction among members that organized opposition reasserted itself for the first time in many years. Reconstructing an opposition movement was hard work. Frank Schonfeld ran for District Coulcil 9 secretary-treasurer in 1961. He lost, but did so with 42% of the vote, a considerable turnout against Rarback's machine. The day after the 1961 election, the Rarback administration sued Schonfeld and others for libel, and Schonfeld lost his job. In response to these actions, and to strengthen and protect the growing dissident movement, he launched a public campaign, with help from Herman Benson, who went on to form the Association for Union Democracy, and Burton Hall, a labor attorney. A meeting was organized to support the development of an independent inter-union judiciary, to be patterned on the United Auto Workers' public review board. Speakers included Norman Thomas, the noted socialist, Dan House of the UAW, Herman Benson, and Schonfeld.
The fight was on, in New York as well as in other parts of the country. Dissidents were physically beaten, and two, Dow Wilson and Lloyd Green, were assassinated in San Francisco. Others were dragged into court, and a running war of internal union charges and counter-charges ensued. The International, which in general supported the incumbent administration, was required to step in and impose a trusteeship in DC 9, a move that served to buffer the Rarback machine. Schonfeld was blocked from running in 1964. In 1966, in one of the many legal tactics he undertook with the assistance of Burton Hall, Schonfeld successfully challenged the trusteeship (Schonfeld v. Raftery). Schonfeld subsequently ran again for DC 9 secretary-treasurer, benefiting from the actions of the U.S. District Court Judge, who not only ordered a supervised, district-wide election, but also required the union to mail a copy of his 67-page opinion on the corrupt tactics of the incumbents to each union member. Schonfeld won. He held office for two terms, and was opposed almost continually during that time.
Schonfeld carried out several reforms during his administration. These included revising the District Council by-laws to require that the American Arbitration Association (AAA) supervise district elections; ending restrictive nominating procedures (as well as the "packing" of locals during nominations); and stipulating that union insurance fund trustees be elected directly by membership. Shop stewards were limited to one-year terms and stewardships were distributed to the locals by lottery, thereby decentralizing Rarback's former network. Schonfeld also convened numerous district-wide membership meetings. In 1972, Schonfeld was brought up on internal union charges (see Penza v. Schonfeld). He was found guilty by the union trial board on charges later determined to be unfounded. The ousted machine campaigned heavily against him, and in 1973, Schonfeld lost his position to James Bishop, a candidate promoted by Rarback's Progressive Painters Club.
While Schonfeld's status as an officer in the District Council ended with the 1973 election, he continued to fight for reform. He served as trustee of the insurance fund in 1977, and president of Bronx Local 19 in 1978. In 1977, Schonfeld's campaign against corruption in the District Council led to the imposition of another trusteeship. The 1977-78 trusteeship, imposed by the International union, helped consolidate the eighteen Painters locals into six, and established citywide election of business agents, with elections supervised by the AAA. However, the Bishop administration was successful in its attempts to evade the monitors, and at this point mob domination of the District Council solidified. Bishop was murdered by the mob in 1990, and the steady attrition of the District Council leadership through indictments, guilty pleas and jail sentences revealed the layers of corruption that had pervaded the Council since Schonfeld's ouster.
After retiring from the union in 1982, Schonfeld remained very active in political and community affairs, serving on the board of the Amalgamated Housing Corporation as treasurer, while studying and volunteering at Lehman College in the Bronx, and working with Herman Benson and the Association for Union Democracy. He died on November 2, 2011.
Scope and Contents
The Frank Schonfeld Papers provide an inside view of a trade distinguished by highly volatile employment cycles, corrupt practices, and successive waves of different ethnic groups making up the workforce, and document the possibilities for establishing some degree of union democracy through rank-and-file campaigns. Much of the legislation that resulted from these efforts resulted in legal reforms that have benefited members in other unions, and contributed to the formation of the Association for Union Democracy.
This collection consists of correspondence, minutes, financial reports, an unpublished manuscript, drafts and statements of materials by Louis Weinstock and Frank Schonfeld, and litigation records of District Council 9 (DC9). Also included in the collection are documents from internal trials, minutes of meetings of the board of trustees, materials relating to the amalgamation of locals, election records and materials from various rank-and-file groups spearheaded by Schonfeld. Newspaper clippings, by-law and referenda campaign materials, and collective bargaining agreements give further insight into the internal disputes within DC 9. Approximately 200 black and white photographs document the 1968 strike, as well as the general membership and officials of the Local. Also included in this collection are materials pertaining to the California Painters Local 4 and proceedings of the New York State Conference of Painters and the International Brotherhood of Painters.
Arrangement
Series I through VI are in rough chronological order; files in Series VII are grouped by legal case or trial; VIII includes minutes followed by subject files; IX is organized alphabetically; XI-XIV are grouped by organization or subject; X and XV-XX are organized in rough chronological order. Series XXI and XXII have not been arranged by an archivist.
Organized into 21 series:
Series I: Correspondence, 1909-1989
Series II: Statements, 1909-1991
Series III: Minutes, 1942-1981
Series IV: Financial Reports, 1941-1991
Series V: District Council 9 Trusteeship Records, 1966-1991
Series VI: Litigation Records, 1962-1990
Series VII: Internal Trials, 1927-1979
Series VIII: Insurance Funds, 1938-1994
Series IX: Suject Files, 1940-1981
Series X: Election Records, 1934-1992
Series XI: Rank-and-File Groups, 1961-1980
Series XII: California Painters, 1961-1977
Series XIII: Clippings, 1946-1992
Series XIV: By-Laws, 1960-1993
Series XV: Referenda, 1960-1993
Series XVI: Collective Bargaining Agreements, 1926-1978
Series XVII: Strikes and Work Stoppages, 1939-1977
Series XVIII: Proceedings, 1946-1992
Series XIX: Publications and Ephemera, 1909-1992
Series XX: Photographs, 1940-1973
Series XXI. 2014 Accretion: Unpublished Manuscript, 1950s
Series XXII: Unprocessed Materials, 1927-1988
Series I through VI are in rough chronological order; files in Series VII are grouped by legal case or trial; VIII includes minutes followed by subject files; IX is organized alphabetically; XI-XIV are grouped by organization or subject; X and XV-XIX are organized in rough chronological order.
Organized into 19 series:
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Burton Hall Papers (WAG 087)
Burton Hall Union Democracy Oral History Collection (OH 034)
Carl Blum Papers (WAG 100)
Daniel French Papers (WAG 101)
Herman Benson, "Insurgency and Reform in the Painters, 1960-1987" in Tamiment Library Vertical Files (Author File)
Louis Weinstock Papers (WAG 013)
International Brotherhood of Painters and Allied Trades, District Council 9: Trusteeship Records (WAG 149)
International Brotherhood of Painters and Allied Trades, District Council 9 Records (WAG 150).
International Brotherhood of Painters and Allied Trades, Local 490 Records (WAG 42)
International Brotherhood of Painters and Allied Trades, Local 874 Records (WAG 152)
Sam Winn Papers (WAG 203)
Correspondence.; Hearings (event); Indictments (legal documents).; Legal documents.; Labor leaders -- New York (State) -- New York.; Collective labor agreements -- Painters, Industrial -- New York (State) -- New York.; Minutes (administrative records); Labor unions -- Corrupt practices -- New York (State) -- New York.; Labor disputes -- New York (State) -- New York.; Painters, Industrial -- New York (State) -- New York.; Photographs.; Labor unions and communism.; Labor union democracy -- New York (State) -- New York.; Painters, Industrial -- Labor unions -- New York (State) -- New York.; International Brotherhood of Painters and Allied Trades; Brotherhood of Painters, Decorators, and Paperhangers of America. Local 490 (New York, N.Y.); United Rank and File Painters Social Clubs of Greater New York; Rarback, Martin; Brotherhood of Painters, Decorators, and Paperhangers of America. Local 848 (New York, N.Y.); Bishop, James; International Brotherhood of Painters and Allied Trades. Painters District Council 9 of New York City; Arnold, Frank; Hall, Burton; French, Daniel, 1908-; Weinstock, Louis, 1903-1994; Schonfeld, Frank; Schonfeld, David
- Series I: Correspondence, 1909-1989
  Scope and Content Note
  Includes notes and drafts of materials prepared by Schonfeld.
  - Correspondence: District Council (DC) 9 and IBPAT, 1909-1989; 1946-1989 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence: New York City DC 9, 1953-1980 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - F. Schonfeld: Correspondence, 1961-1966 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - F. Schonfeld: Correspondence, 1967-1969 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - F. Schonfeld: Correspondence, 1970-1972 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - F. Schonfeld: Correspondence, 1973-1984 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - F. Schonfeld: Correspondence with Summers; Rauh, 1967, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - F. Schonfeld: Jurisdictional Dispute with Carpenters, 1969-1972 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - F. Schonfeld: Replies to B. Hall (New Politics), 1973 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - F. Schonfeld: Correspondence with UMW; other Unions and Orgs., 1971-1973 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - F. Schonfeld: Letter to NY Times in re Corruption and Government Contracts, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - F. Schonfeld: Correspondence, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - F. Schonfeld" Notes, 1957-1980, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Local Union 1011: Correspondence (United Painters Club, etc.), 1939-1962 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - F. Schonfeld: Correspondence: Local Union 1011 etc., 1948-1961 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - F. Schonfeld: Correspondence: Local Union 1011 etc., 1962-1963 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - F. Schonfeld: Correspondence: Local Union 1011 etc., 1964 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - F. Schonfeld: Correspondence: Local Union 1011 etc.; Notes, 1965-1969, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Local 1011: Report, June 1977 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence - Local Union 19 - Candidacy for Business Rep., 1978-1984 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Local Union 19: Candidacy for Business Rep.: Notes, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Local Union 19: Appeal and Reply, Dues Increase Referendum, 1978-1983 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Local Union 19: Financial Reports, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Local Union 19: By-Laws and Preparations for, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Local Union 19: F. Schonfeld: Notes, 1977-1981, undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Notes; Drafts: F. Schonfeld, 1961-1989, undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Notes: DC 9: F. Schonfeld, 1975-1977 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - F. Schonfeld: Drafts, Notes, Statements, 1977, undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Series II: Statements, 1909-1991
  Includes materials by Louis Weinstock and Frank Schonfeld, as well as a statement from 1909 issued by Local Union 1011.
  - Local Union 1011: Statement on Injunction, 1909 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Louis Weinstock: Speeches, 1946-1947 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - F. Schonfeld: Speeches, Statements, 1961-1991 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - F. Schonfeld: Speech Material, Notes, undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Series III: Minutes, 1942-1981
  Consists of minutes of District Council 9 meetings.
  - District Council 9: Minutes, 1942 February 4, 1942 July 15 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - DC 9: Minutes, 1946-1961 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - DC 9: Minutes, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - DC 9: Minutes, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - DC 9: Minutes, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - DC 9: Minutes, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - DC 9: Minutes, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - DC 9: Minutes, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - DC 9: Minutes, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - DC 9: Minutes, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - DC 9: Minutes, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - DC 9: Minutes, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - DC 9: Minutes, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - DC 9: Minutes, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - DC 9: Minutes, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - DC 9: Minutes, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - DC 9: Minutes, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - DC 9: Minutes, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - DC 9: Minutes, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - DC 9 - Minutes, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - DC 9: Minutes, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - DC 9: Minutes, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - DC 9: Minutes, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - DC 9: Minutes, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - DC 9: Minutes, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - DC 9: Minutes, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - DC 9: Minutes, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - DC 9: Minutes, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - DC 9: Minutes, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - DC 9: Minutes, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - DC 9: Minutes, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - DC 9: Minutes, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - DC 9: Minutes, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - DC 9: Minutes, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - DC 9: Minutes, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - DC 9: Minutes, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - DC 9: Minutes, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - DC 9: Minutes, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - DC 9: Minutes, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - DC 9: Minutes, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - DC 9: Minutes, 1974-1975 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - DC 9: Minutes, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - DC 9: Minutes, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - DC 9: Minutes, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - DC 9: Minutes, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - DC 9: Minutes, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - DC 9: Minutes, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - DC 9: Minutes, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - DC 9: Minutes, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - DC 9: Minutes, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - DC 9: Minutes, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - DC 9: Minutes (Inc.), 1978 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - DC 9: Minutes, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - DC 9: Minutes, 1980-1981 (Box 4, Folder 17)
- Series IV: Financial Reports, 1941-1991
  Contains financial reports of District Council 9.
  - Financial Report, DC 9, 1941 October 1 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Financial Reports, DC 9, 1951-1959 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Financial Reports, DC 9, 1962-1965 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Financial Reports, DC 9, 1966-1969 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Financial Reports, DC 9, 1969-1973 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Financial Reports, DC 9, 1973-1991 (Box 4, Folder 23)
- Series V: District Council 9 Trusteeship Records, 1966-1991
  Includes the 1966-67 hearings on trusteeship in the wake of the Rarback corruption scandal; the 1977 trusteeship hearings; and material on the last trusteeship in 1990-91, following the murder of James Bishop.
  - Special Trusteeship: Hearing in Continuation of (1 of 2), 1966 November 3 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Special Trusteeship: Hearing (2 of 2), 1966 November 3 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Special Trusteeship: Hearing (1 of 2; pp. 276-432), 1966 November 4 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Special Trusteeship: Hearing (2 of 2; pp. 433-571), 1966 November 4 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Special Trusteeship: Hearing (1 of 2; pp. 573-712), 1966 November 9 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Special Trusteeship: Hearing (2 of 2; pp. 713-859), 1966 November 9 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Trusteeship Action - Burton Hall, Retainer (F.S., et. al.), 1967 March 3 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Trusteeship: Transcript of Hearing, 1977 January 7 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Trusteeship: Statement of DC 9 in Opposition to, 1977 May 2 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Trusteeship: Selected Exhibits - Hearing, 1977 May 11-1977 June 20 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Trusteeship: Transcript of Hearing (1 of 2), 1977 May 11 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Trusteeship: Transcript of Hearing (2 of 2), 1977 May 11 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Trusteeship: Transcript of Hearing, 1977 May 12 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Trusteeship: Transcript of Hearing (1 of 2), 1977 May 16 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Trusteeship: Transcript of Hearing (2 of 2), 1977 May 16 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Trusteeship: Transcript of Hearing (1 of 2), 1977 May 17 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Trusteeship: Transcript of Hearing (2 of 2), 1977 May 17 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Trusteeship: Transcript of Hearing (1 of 2), 1977 May 19 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Trusteeship: Transcript of Hearing (2 of 2), 1977 May 19 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Trusteeship: Transcript of Hearing, 1977 May 20 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Trusteeship: Transcript of Hearing, 1977 May 25 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Trusteeship: Transcript of Hearing, 1977 June 1 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Trusteeship: Transcript of Hearing, 1977 June 3 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Trusteeship: Transcript of Hearing (1 of 2), 1977 June 8 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Trusteeship: Transcript of Hearing (2 of 2), 1977 June 8 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Trusteeship: Transcript of Hearing (1 of 4), 1977 June 9 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Trusteeship: Transcript of Hearing (2 of 4), 1977 June 9 (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Trusteeship: Transcript of Hearing (3 of 4), 1977 June 9 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Trusteeship: Transcript of Hearing (4 of 4), 1977 June 9 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Trusteeship: Transcript of Hearing (1 of 3), 1977 June 16 (Box 6, Folder 3)